Okay, this is the second part of our
update for April 24th, Friday um
artificial intelligence updates,
miscellaneous updates and uh the
epigraph here end every session by
telling the model to update the skill.
Well, actually telling the agent to
update the skill. So, it's coming from
Sabrina Ramanov and uh yeah, she she's
absolutely amazing. She's doing
marketing very aggressively uh using AI
agents. So open Mthos. So this
22year-old
Kai Gomez he started this project. It's
open source in on GitHub and what it's
trying to do he's trying to reverse
engineer anthropic mus architecture.
Well, Mus is kind of secretive, but
there is some uh information available
in public sources and uh so he created a
small model. It's 770 million parameter
model and it's using uh recurrent. So
you re-enter the same layer over and
over and over again, right? So up to 16
times and this uh recussion makes the
model much better. So research suggests
that 77
70 million parameter version can match
1.3 uh standard transformer.
Yeah. Uh so this is very interesting uh
project. So you can check it on GitHub.
Uh next
symbolic AI cuts energy use by 100
times.
This is not new. I was talking about it
in previous uh updates. Uh so AI now
consumes over 10% of US electricity
a lot of money. Researchers announced
neuros symbolic AI system that cuts
energy use by 100 times while actually
improving accuracy. Right. [snorts]
Additional efficiency breakthroughs
include turbo quant algorithm. Yeah I
was talking about this previously. For
businesses this means AI tools once
limited to enterprise budgets will
become affordable for every everyone.
Please mute yourself, Bella.
>> Please mute yourself. Yeah. Okay. Uh
let's go next. Uh Yan Lun Leorld model.
So he was arguing for years that LLMs is
a dead end. It's not the way to go. Uh
long argued that generative AI waste
compute memor memorizing patterns
instead of understanding the reality.
His alternative called Japa uh predicts
abstract concepts rather than raw pixels
in the world but suffered from
representation collapse and this new
paper they found a solution which is
mathematical real ghoul ariser forcing
the model to internalize physical
structure. The result is small model
only 15 million parameter model that
trains on one GPU in just few hours
plans 48 times faster than massive
foundation models and generally
understands physics. Yeah, we spoke
about it. I just want to repeat it. It's
extremely important topic. Uh these are
some updates of open claw on GitHub. It
already has 363,000
stars. And you see updates are coming
every day, every second day. A lot of
updates, very, very massive. And another
thing about Hermes agent, it's also
becoming very popular. You see, it's now
already has 115,000 stars and also
updates. And this updates massive. If if
you go to this link and just look how
many new features, how many oh it says
here 1,500 commits,
761 merged uh PRs and so on. This is
huge. So this is interface release. This
is like cool uh tool gateway release. Um
huge progress. Hermas uh looks like a
very very good agent. Okay. uh five
advanced open source tools for cloud
code. Uh very useful video uh shows some
tooling you can use with clot code. I
will not go through this. Uh some
entropic news they released the live
artifacts in co-work for auto updating
dashboards. They added new connectors
for all trails instacart audible trip
advisor turbo tax and so on so on. So um
cloud is becoming uh uh more and more
and more like practical. Uh clude is now
available inside Microsoft Word but only
for pro or max users. So if you pay
money you have it. Antropic news. Oh
this is I just said okay Google deep
mind deep research max uh autonomous
research agent built on Gemini 3.1 Pro.
[snorts] Uh can run a lot of searches
does it in parallel. Supports MCP and
web search. Multimodel imports. natively
generates charts and infographic in
line. Deep mind was always very good at
doing research but this is the latest
version. Okay. Many other warp edit
universal agent support. Microsoft
copilot gained agentic uh capabilities
right inside world Excel or PowerPoint.
XI rolled out custom timelines powered
by Grog. Hey genen is excellent if you
haven't looked at it. uh it can generate
uh your avatar like talking in the
video. In fact, we're planning to to do
it. Uh they launched hyperframes for AI
generated animations,
ideoggram, added custom model training.
Four robots finished a half marathon in
China. Yeah, China is ahead of the rest
of the world in robotics. Xi Gro text to
speech. Okay, this is good quality API
at 5% error rate versus uh 11 laps 12%.
Well, 11 laps is default standard top of
the line and now uh Grog text to speech
is better and uh affordable. Okay. Open
AI, GPT resolind and GPT 54 cyber. Uh
new life scientist model built for
biology, drug discovery, genomics and
protein engineering. And cyber is
different. It focuses on defensive
security featuring binary code analysis,
vulnerability detection and and so on.
OpenAI also updated agents SDK with
model native harness and and so on.
Okay. And uh next yeah this is
interesting. So he describes the life of
engineer and he says that well code is
now generated by agents and is generated
very fast a lot of code. So code becomes
absolutely free and abundant. Engineers
are now steering agents. They are not
writing code themselves. And the scarce
resource today are human time attention
and model context.
And uh yeah, engineers should be like
staff level orchestrators, steering
agents, uh harness engineering success
depends on docu documenting
nonfunctional requirements, eliminating
slope systematically and progressively
removing humans from the loop. The goal
is to fully autonomous pipeline driven
by token budget and clear priorities.
Okay. Um Google similar. So this is to
generate training data. You want to
create synthetic data to train your
model and you want this data to be high
quality and this is like a really
comprehensive uh coverage, diversity,
complexity, quality. U so yeah this is
the tool from Google uh anthropic. Yes,
this is the problem uh which is
discussed everywhere. Not enough
compute.
uh in comparison um X AI have a lot of
uh hardware uh so they they have compute
but not in such demand. Everybody wants
Antropic. Uh and by the way, yeah, XAI
partnered with Corser. Okay, here I have
it. Ellen Musk rocket and space company
announced partnership with Corserai. The
deal gives SpaceX option to either
acquire Corser later for $60 billion or
pay 10 billion for collaborative work if
no acquisition will happen. Okay, but
returning to this list. So we have XAI,
we have Google which has uh a lot of
hardware and has a lot of demand and uh
yeah and they're selling TPUs to uh
other providers while serving Germany
also on TPUs. Open AAI you know they
were spending so much money on
infrastructure they are in high demand
and they have enough compute and
entropic everybody wants it demand rich
but compute starved [laughter]
the economics for entropic entropic
can't raise prices because then people
will switch to other vendors and can't
serve demand so they're using quarter
manipulation as a stealth price hike so
they reduce subscription quarters.
Jensen Huang about Nvidia. This is very
good. Oh, I didn't provide the link but
it's on YouTube. It's pretty lengthy
about 2 hours. But one of the things he
was saying that China already has
abundant energy chips and researchers.
So uh he says that export controls are
absolutely not effective and what they
may create is isolation and China and
without like using American technology
whatever China will just go ahead and
will develop faster. It's actually
better for American not to uh isolate
but work together
and uh yes now Abacus Aai you know they
have deep agent and now they have this
new idea agent swarms uh so they start a
lot of agents working in parallel. So
they have master agent which controls
many many worker agents and you see
intelligence emerging through
coordination rather than just larger
single models and they provide multiple
examples how it is uh very effective.
Uh next AI attributed layoffs uh will
grow nine times in uh this year later
this year. So companies are suppressing
hiring. Entry-level postings uh dropped
while AI focused roles surged 340%.
Well, this we were talking all the time.
You need to be AI specialist and
position yourself uh as such on the job
market and uh there are multiple
examples. Consensus.appup
uh yeah this is interesting. This is
search engine for academic uh papers. AI
powered academic search engine searches
over 220 million peer-reviewed research
papers and provides uh the report
grounded in real studies with verifiable
citations. Uh very good. There is a free
layer and then there are paid layer. So
yeah, it's a good good thing. Uh oh yeah
[snorts] this is Sabrina Romanov and
yeah she she's absolutely amazing. She
created a service which is called blot
data and this is the website blota.com.
So she uses clo code and this service to
do uh marketing and you see she built
1.4 million uh people audience using
these tools and in in this video she
describes how she does it. She she
produces a lot of content but she still
reviews this content before it is
published and uh yeah so she created a
lot of skills and skills to convert from
one platform to another. Uh she posts on
LinkedIn, Facebook X all entirely
through Claude. You see manually reviews
every post to ensure brand integrity.
Yeah. Oh yeah. and she recommends ending
every session by telling Claude to
update the skill based on the feedback
given during the conversation. Very
simple, right? Uh next um Mlop's uh
model uh life cycle management. Well, if
you are doing AI in a corporation and
you use different models and you're
versioning them and you're testing them
and moving them in production, you need
some system uh to manage all that and
there are two uh solutions which are
recommended. One is weight and biases
which is very famous. It's AI
development platform trusted by
thousands of companies including OpenAI
and NVIDIA
for building, training, evaluating,
monitoring ML models. So this is the
screen. So you see how what's happening
with the models. So weights and biases
they have their YouTube channel
very good uh core product tracks
experiments real time interactive
dashboards and so on. And uh then MLflow
is different. It's open source. Uh you
in fact can just import it from your
Python script and start using it. It
provides experiment tracking like you
see here. Uh logging parameters,
metrics, model artifacts across training
runs. Uh model registry. Well, this one
also has model registry of course. Uh
governant version control store where
models move through staging, production
and archiving. Supports automated
deployment uh and and so on. So these
are two thing things to consider if
you're building it in real life. Okay.
AI pretends to be a scientist.
Oh gosh. So this is the study. This is
archive linked to to the paper and what
they found is actually scary. So people
were saying that AI can do scientific
work. But apparently it's not reasoning.
You see in 68% of cases AI agents
gathered evidence and then ignored it.
In 71% they never updated their beliefs
at all. Uh the researchers call it
evidence non. So they pretend to be
scientists but they are not actually
scientists.
Okay. Oh this is this is actually what
what I did. I asked AI to make a list of
things to do to live longer and then to
sort it putting the most important
factors on top and this is the list and
I thought it will put on top uh things
related to health like eat less,
exercise more but actually no it put on
top manage chronic stress and then
maintain strong uh social relationship,
avoid isolation.
So social life and uh relaxation that's
what we need to do. Okay. Don't smoke.
Then this blue ones is related to
physical health like eating, physical
activity and healthy body weight. And
then health a sense of purpose. Uh I guy
uh sleep enough and get regular medical
checkups. Okay. Uh this is uh about
jobs. So, in April, oh, Meta laid off uh
a lot of people. And uh then that's me
as usual. And thank you